Amelia Olenio Collection of American Woolen Company Photographs 6502 P
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Amelia Olenio Collection of American Woolen Company Photographs
1910-1955
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Olenio, Amelia
American Woolen Company
6502 P
0.33 cubic feet
0.3 linear ft.
Gelatin silver print, photographs.
Photographs of overseers' outings, company executives, the March 1936 Lawrence, Massachusetts, flood, and other subjects.
10060561
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
R. Miles, October 03, 2017
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, November 08, 2017
Biographical / Historical
The American Woolen Company was founded in 1899 under the direction of William M. Wood and Frederick Ayer. In the 1920s the company owned and operated 60 woolen mills, at which time it controlled 20% of the U.S. woolen production. Despite several changes in ownership, the American Woolen Company is still in operation and is a designer, manufacturer and distributor of men's and women's worsted and woolen fabrics. Based in Stafford Springs, Connecticut, the company operates from the 160-year-old Warren Mills, which it acquired from Loro Piana SpA in June 2014.
Scope and Contents
Photographs of American Woolen Mills overseers' outings, which include men and women playing games.
The company executive photographs include president Francis W. White, vice-president William Muir, purchasing agent Percy Wardwell, general sales manager Charles H. Silver, manager of costs Rory Veitch, treasurer F. S. Connett, vice-president and comptroller George E. McClellan, and public relations executive Jack Barry.
Photographers include Alton Anderson and George Valentine Enell.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 6502 PUBS: Amelia Olenio Collection of American Woolen Company Publications 5129: Maxwell Copelof Arbitration Briefs, Exhibits, Transcripts and Decisions 5131: Sidney A. Wolff Arbitration Files 5583/4: Archives Organization File (AOF) Part 4. Corporate and Organizational Publications 6046: Archives Union File (AUF) 6510: American Woolen Company Collection 6510 PUBS: American Woolen Company Publications 6510/001: American Woolen Company Records
Boats and boating; Clothing and dress; Display of merchandise; Drawing -- Powered -- Pin drafter; Executives; Fishing; Flood -- 1936; Flood damage; Floods; Outdoor games; Outdoor recreation; Recreation; Spectators; Supervisors; Textile factories; Textile industry; Textile industry -- Massachusetts; Textile machinery; Textile workers; Women employees; Women's clothing; Woolen and worsted drawing; Woolen and worsted manufacture; Andover (Mass.); Lawrence (Mass.); Shawsheen River (Mass.); Shawsheen Village (Mass.); Anderson, Alton; Barry, Jack; Buckley, John J.; Connett, F. S.; Enell, George Valentine; Demers, Walter; McClellan, George E.; Muir, William; Silver, Charles H.; Veitch, Rory; Wardwell, Percy; White, Francis W. (Francis Wilford), 1893-1957; White, John; Warner & Swasey; Wood Worsted Mill (Lawrence, Mass.)
10060561
- Overseers Outing and Fishing, 1920-1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 1: Overseers outing, American Woolen Company, Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Image depicts group of overseers of American Woolen Company posed outdoors. 9 x 6 cm.
    Format: Black and White photograph.
  - Item 2: Two unidentified men, overseers outing, American Woolen Company, 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts two unidentified men at an outing of overseers of American Woolen Company. Both men wear three-piece suits and hats; may be executives (?) at American Woolen. 6.75 x 11 cm.
  - Item 3: Spectators, overseers outing, American Woolen Company, 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts women and men sitting on sidelines of unseen game at an outing of overseers of American Woolen Company. 11.5 x 7 cm.
  - Item 4: Unidentified man, overseers outing, American Woolen Company, 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts unidentified older man wearing glasses, holding a cap in his hand, and wearing watch chain. Two men in background also unidentified. All at an outing of overseers of American Woolen Company. 6.75 x 11.5 cm.
  - Item 5: Unidentified man with baseball bat, overseers outing, American Woolen Company, 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts unidentified older man in full suit, tie and hat, carrying a baseball bat on his left shoulder. Possibly an executive at American Woolen Company. 6 x 9 cm.
  - Item 6: Group of overseers/executives, overseers outing, American Woolen Company, 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts group of unidentified men, who may be overseers or executives (or a mix of the two), at an overseers outing of the American American Woolen Company. All wear suits (most in three-piece suits), ties and hats or caps. 11.5 x 6.75 cm.
  - Item 7: Group of overseers, overseers outing, American Woolen Company, 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts group of unidentified men, presumably overseers for the American Woolen Company at an overseers outing of the company. 11.5 x 7.25 cm.
  - Item 8: Tug-o-war, overseers outing, American Woolen Company, 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts group of men playing tug-o-war at an overseers outing of the American Woolen Company. 11.25 x 6.5 cm.
  - Item 9: Recreational games, overseers outing, American Woolen Company, 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts group of men playing unknown game at an overseers outing of the American Woolen Company. 11.5 x 7 cm.
  - Item 10: Footrace, overseers outing, American Woolen Company, 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts group of men engaged in a footrace at an overseers outing of the American Woolen Company. 11.5 x 7 cm.
  - Item 11: Baseball game, overseers outing, American Woolen Company, 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts group of men engaged in a baseball game at an overseers outing of the American Woolen Company. 11.5 x 7 cm.
  - Item 12: Preparing for tug-o-war, overseers outing, American Woolen Company, 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts group of men about to engage in a game of tug-o-war (see 0000.1169.57) at an overseers outing of the American Woolen Company. 11.5 x 7 cm.
  - Item 13: Unidentified men preparing for baseball game, overseers outing, American Woolen Company, 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts group of men preparing to play baseball at an overseers outing of the American Woolen Company. 11.5 x 7.25 cm.
  - Item 14: Unidentified men preparing for baseball game, overseers outing, American Woolen Company, 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts group of men preparing to play baseball at an overseers outing of the American Woolen Company. 11 x 6.75 cm.
  - Item 15: Group of overseers, overseers outing, American Woolen Company, 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts group of unidentified men, presumably overseers for the American Woolen Company at an overseers outing of the company. Virtually identical to 0000.1169.56; clearly taken a moment earlier or later. 11.5 x 7.25 cm.
  - Item 16: Men and women engaged in unknown game, overseers outing, American Woolen Company, 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts a group of men and women participating in some sort of game or contest at an overseers outing of the American Woolen Company. 11.5 x 7 cm.
  - Item 17: Footrace, overseers outing, American Woolen Company, 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts a group of men watching another man race at an overseers outing of the American Woolen Company. 11.5 x 7.25 cm.
  - Item 18: Women at overseers outing, American Woolen Company, 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts a group of women at an overseers outing of the American Woolen Company. 11.5 x 7 cm.
  - Item 19: Group of men at overseers outing, American Woolen Company, 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts a group of men at an overseers outing of the American Woolen Company, probably preparing to play a game of some sort. 11 x 6.75 cm.
  - Item 20: Spectators at overseers outing, American Woolen Company, 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts men and women seated in a line, waiting to observe a footrace or game of some sort at an overseers outing of the American Woolen Company. 11 x 6.75 cm.
  - Item 21: Preparing for a game at overseers outing, American Woolen Company, 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts several men preparing for a game of some sort at an overseers outing of the American Woolen Company. Note spectators seated in background. 11.5 x 7 cm.
  - Item 22: Unidentified man (overseer?), overseers outing, American Woolen Company, 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts unidentified man, presumably an overseer, at an overseers outing of the American Woolen Company. The man is dressed in vest and pants, with tie and watch chain. 7.25 x 11.5 cm.
  - Item 23: Baseball game, overseers outing, American Woolen Company, 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts several men participating in a baseball game at an overseers outing of the American Woolen Company. 11.5 x 7.25 cm.
  - Item 24: Spectators, overseers outing, American Woolen Company, 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts spectators in the distance at an overseers outing of the American Woolen Company. 11 x 6.75 cm.
  - Item 25: Sports, overseers outing, American Woolen Company, 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts several men participating in unknown sport (game of catch?) at an overseers outing of the American Woolen Company. 11.5 x 6.75 cm.
  - Item 26: Unidentified man, overseers outing, American Woolen Company, 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts an unidentified man, possibly management (?), at an overseers outing of the American Woolen Company. Man is dressed in three-piece suit, wearing a tie, hat, and watch chain, holding a cigar or cigarette in his right hand. 6.75 x 11.5 cm.
  - Item 27: Three-legged race, overseers outing, American Woolen Company, 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts several men participating in a three-legged race at an overseers outing of the American Woolen Company. 11.5 x 7 cm.
  - Item 28: At the finish line, overseers outing, American Woolen Company, 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts several men participating in a footrace, with the winner just approaching the finish line (a string held across the field at the finish line) at an overseers outing of the American Woolen Company. 11.5 x 6.75 cm.
  - Item 29: Long jump competition, overseers outing, American Woolen Company, 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts one man participating in a long jump competition at an overseers outing of the American Woolen Company. 11.5 x 7 cm.
  - Item 30: Fishing competition, overseers outing, American Woolen Company, 1945-1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts two men displaying the fish they caught at an overseers outing of the American Woolen Company. The man on the right (in the hat) is also depicted in folder 1, item 32. 10 x 9.75 cm.
  - Item 31: Boating expedition, overseers outing, American Woolen Company, 1945-1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts small powerboat on unknown lake or pond at an overseers outing of the American Woolen Company. 10 x 9.75 cm.
  - Item 32: Fishing, overseers outing, American Woolen Company, 1945-1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts man holding several fish he apparently caught at an overseers outing of the American Woolen Company. The same man is also seen in folder 1, item 30. 10 x 9.75 cm.
- Shawsheen Village, Andover, Mass., 1936; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 1: Administration Building, Shawsheen Village, Andover, Mass., 1936; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
    March 20, 1936. Image depicts flood of March 1936. The Adnministration Building housed the executive offices of the American Woolen Company. Note the rowboat with two figures in it in the center background, and the building almost entirely covered by floo
  - Item 2: Balmoral Spa, Shawsheen Village, Andover, Mass., 1936; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
    March 20, 1936. Image depicts flood of March 1936. The Balmoral Spa, built by the American Woolen Company as part of the planned village of Shawsheen, housed a drug store, barber shop, hairdresser, offices and a dance hall. The flood waters of the Shawshe
  - Item 3: Den Rock Road, Shawsheen Village, Andover, Mass., 1936; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
    March 20, 1936. Image depicts flood of March 1936. Photograph was taken at 3:00 p.m. Den Rock Road is the present-day Route 114 that runs through Lawrence and Andover, Mass. This is probably in the Shawsheen Village area, which was home to the American Wo
  - Item 4: Balmoral Spa, Shawsheen Village, Andover, Mass., 1936; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
- 300,000 lbs. wet top -- Wood Mill, Lawrence, Mass., 1927; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 1: About 300,000 lbs. of wet top at Wood Mill, Lawrence, Mass., 1927; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Image depicts pounds of wet top in Wood Mill yard, American Woolen Company, Lawrence, Mass. Typed on reverse: "Nov. 14 - 18 - 1927 About 300,000 lbs. of Wet Top." Top is a ball of wool or manufactured fiber (in this case wool) generally weighing 5 to 15 p
  - Item 2: About 300,000 lbs. of wet top at Wood Mill, Lawrence, Mass., 1927; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 3: About 300,000 lbs. of wet top at Wood Mill, Lawrence, Mass., 1927; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 4: About 300,000 lbs. of wet top at Wood Mill, Lawrence, Mass., 1927; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Wood Mill, Lawrence, Mass. -- Flood of March 1936, Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Item 1: Duck Bridge, Lawrence, Mass., 1936; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    March 20, 1936. Image depicts flood of March 1936. Written on reverse of Copy B: "Duck Bridge, taken from Card Room (Wood Mill), Friday, [March] 20, 1936 (9:00 A.M.)." The Duck Bridge, whose formal name was the Union Street Bridge, ran between Union and S
  - Item 2: Wood Mill yard taken from the supply room, Lawrence, Mass., 1936; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    March 19, 1936. Image depicts the yard of the Wood Mill (owned by the American Woolen Co.) in Lawrence, Mass., taken from the supply room on Thursday, March 19, 1936 at 3 p.m. Notice the little wooden shed, which appears to shift slightly in the next phot
  - Item 3: Wood Mill yard, Lawrence, Mass., 1936; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    March 19, 1936. Image depicts the yard of the Wood Mill (owned by the American Woolen Co.) in Lawrence, Mass., taken from the supply room on Thursday, March 19, 1936 at 3 p.m. Notice the little wooden shed, which appears to have shifted slightly from the
  - Item 4: Wood Mill yard taken from the supply room, Lawrence, Mass., 1936; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    March 19, 1936. Image depicts the yard of the Wood Mill (owned by the American Woolen Co.) in Lawrence, Mass., taken from the supply room on Thursday, March 19, 1936 at 3 p.m. Notice the little wooden shed, which appears to shift slightly in another photo
  - Item 5: Duck Bridge, Lawrence, Mass., 1936; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Item 6: Duck Bridge, Lawrence, Mass., 1936; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    March 19, 1936. Image depicts flood of March 1936. Written on reverse: "Duck Bridge, taken from Wood Mill roof Thurs. Mar. 19, 1936 (3:30 p.m.)." The Duck Bridge, whose formal name was the Union Street Bridge, ran between Union and South Union streets ove
  - Item 7: Wood Mill yard taken from weave room, Lawrence, Mass., 1936; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    March 20, 1936. Image depicts flood of March 1936. Image shows flood waters halfway up Boston & Maine railroad cars in the Wood Mill yard in Lawrence. Written on reverse of Copy B: "Wood Mill yard taken from weave room Friday, March 20, 1936 (9:30 a.m.)."
  - Item 8: Flood damage inside Wood Mill, Lawrence, Mass., 1936; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    March 1936. Image depicts flood damage inside mill, probably the Wood Mill of the American Woolen Company, Lawrence, Mass, during the flood of March 1936. 13 x 18 cm.
  - Item 9: Flooding along the Merrimack River, Lawrence, Mass., 1936; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    March 1936. Image depicts flooding along the Merrimack River; taken from the vantage point of the Wood Mill complex of the American Woolen Company, looking across the river, during the flood of March 1936. 13 x 18 cm.
  - Item 10: Wood Mill yard taken from weave room, Lawrence, Mass., 1936; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Item 11: Cloth Shipping Room, Wood Mill, Lawrence, Mass., 1936; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    March 20, 1936. Image depicts flood damage in Cloth Shipping Room of the Wood Mill, taken from the Cloth Shipping Office. What appears to be a floor beyond the windows is actually water (see 0000.1169.44 for damage in the Cloth Shipping Office). Photo tak
  - Item 12: Cloth Shipping Office, Wood Mill, Lawrence, Mass., 1936; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    March 20, 1936. Image depicts flood damage in Cloth Shipping Office of the Wood Mill. Water still visible nearly up to the windowsill level; desk and chairs broken and floating. Part of the Cloth Shipping Room visible through the windows. Photo taken Frid
- Warner & Swacey pin drafters, Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Item 1: Warner & Swasey pin drafters producing balled slivers., Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
    mage shows male employee of American Woolen Company in Lawrence, Mass., at Warner & Swasey pin drafter. 25.5 x 20.5 cm.
  - Item 2: Warner & Swasey pin drafters delivering balls of slivers., Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Image shows female employee of American Woolen Company in Lawrence, Mass., at Warner & Swasey pin drafter (worsted system) removing ball of slivers. 25.5 x 20.5 cm.
  - Item 3: Warner & Swasey pin drafters delivering balls of slivers, Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Image shows Warner & Swasey pin drafter (worsted system) delivering balls of slivers in the American Woolen Company, Lawrence, Mass. 25.5 x 20.5 cm.
  - Item 4: Warner & Swasey pin drafters delivering balls of slivers, Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Image shows male employee of American Woolen Company in Lawrence, Mass., at Warner & Swasey pin drafter (worsted system) removing ball of slivers. 25.5 x 20.5 cm.
- Bioplays of American Woolen Co. (Spring 1949), Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Item 1: American Woolen Company display: "Cutting"., 1949; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Stamped on reverse: Photo by George Valentine Enell and Assoc., Inc., Hangar 4, La Guardia Field, New York, N.Y. ILlinois 8-9601-2. Image shows American Woolen Company display on cutting for an unknown exhibition in the spring of 1949. Note the lamb weari
  - Item 2: American Woolen Company display: "Washing"., 1949; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Stamped on reverse: Photo by George Valentine Enell and Assoc., Inc., Hangar 4, La Guardia Field, New York, N.Y. ILlinois 8-9601-2. Image shows American Woolen Company display on washing for an unknown exhibition in the spring of 1949. Note the lamb hangi
  - Item 3: American Woolen Company display: "Dyeing"., 1949; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Stamped on reverse: Photo by George Valentine Enell and Assoc., Inc., Hangar 4, La Guardia Field, New York, N.Y. ILlinois 8-9601-2. Image shows American Woolen Company display on dyeing for an unknown exhibition in the spring of 1949. Note the two lambs m
  - Item 4: American Woolen Company display: "Shearing"., 1949; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Stamped on reverse: Photo by George Valentine Enell and Assoc., Inc., Hangar 4, La Guardia Field, New York, N.Y. ILlinois 8-9601-2. Image shows American Woolen Company display on shearing for an unknown exhibition in the spring of 1949. One lamb is sheari
  - Item 5: American Woolen Company display: "Spinning"., 1949; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Stamped on reverse: Photo by George Valentine Enell and Assoc., Inc., Hangar 4, La Guardia Field, New York, N.Y. ILlinois 8-9601-2. Image shows American Woolen Company display on spinning for an unknown exhibition in the spring of 1949. One lamb sits at a
  - Item 6: American Woolen Company display: "Weaving"., 1949; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Stamped on reverse: Photo by George Valentine Enell and Assoc., Inc., Hangar 4, La Guardia Field, New York, N.Y. ILlinois 8-9601-2. Image shows American Woolen Company display on weaving for an unknown exhibition in the spring of 1949. One lamb holds a fr
  - Item 7: American Woolen Company display: "Fashion Show"., 1949; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Stamped on reverse: Photo by George Valentine Enell and Assoc., Inc., Hangar 4, La Guardia Field, New York, N.Y. ILlinois 8-9601-2. Image shows American Woolen Company display of a fashion show for an unknown exhibition in the spring of 1949. One lamb sin
- American Woolen Co. -- Wood Mills, 1910-1931 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Item 1: American Woolen Company Wood Worsted Mills, Lawrence, Mass., 1910; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 7)
    ca1910. Photograph of a photomechanical print of the Wood Worsted Mills complex in Lawrence. Two smoking chimneys at right; a streetcar and early automobile on the street in front of the complex. 24 x 18 cm.
  - Item 2: Wood Worsted Mills, Lawrence, Mass., 1931; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Wood Worsted Mills, Lawrence, Mass. 1931. Image shows the 5-story brick complex owned by the American Woolen Company on the corner of S. Union and Merrimack streets in Lawrence. Written on reverse: "Wood Worsted Mills Lawrence Mass. 2/14/31." 24.5 x 18 cm
  - Item 3: American Woolen Company offices., Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 7)
    mage shows 3-story brick building containing the offices of the American Woolen Company. Behind the offices is a boardinghouse. The North Canal is on the left. Note the truck containing bales of wool. Photo taken in winter. 25.5 x 20.5 cm.
- Various Exec. Of American Woolen Co. (Francis White, President), 1951-1953 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Item 1: Francis W. White at Chamber of Commerce dinner., 1952; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Francis W. White at Chamber of Commerce dinner. Stamped on reverse of photo: "St. Linger Studio, 373 Essex Street, Lawrence, Massachusetts." Three-quarter length view of White (1893-1957), president of the American Woolen Company, in suit, vest and tie, s
  - Item 2: American Woolen Company, Chamber of Commerce dinner., 1952; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Stamped on reverse of photo: "St. Linger Studio, 373 Essex Street, Lawrence, Massachusetts." Standing from left to right: Francis W. White (president, American Woolen Company), Mayor John J. Buckley (mayor of Lawrence), Walter Demers (Chamber of Commerce)
  - Item 3: Francis W. White and John White., 1952; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 8)